A Guide to the Planning, Zoning & Development Department Visual Records of Historic Sites, 1990 - 2004
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Planning, Zoning & Development Department Visual Records of Historic Sites 1990 - 2004
Thomas Balch Library
RG 022
1.5 cu. ft.
This collection is comprised of photographs of historic buildings and sites within and adjacent to the Town of Leesburg. The photographs document changes to existing buildings, buildings demolished for development, and general streetscape photographs of the Old and Historic District documenting its appearance from 1990 to 2004 (with one 1974 photograph). The photographs were taken by the Preservation Planner of the Department of Planning, Zoning & Development of the Town of Leesburg.
Town of Leesburg, Department of Planning, Zoning & Development
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Town of Leesburg, Department of Planning, Zoning & Development
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2005.0001
Historical Information
The Town of Leesburg Department of Planning, Zoning and Development assists the Town Council in developing land use policy and enforces land use and zoning regulations. There are three divisions within the department: comprehensive planning, current planning, and zoning. Their activities include reviewing development plans, processing zoning and special exception applications, and issuing permits. The department employs an Historic Preservation Planner, who provides assistance to property owners in the Old and Historic District with regard to planning matters.
Scope and Content
This collection is comprised of photographs of historic buildings and sites within and adjacent to the Town of Leesburg. The photographs document changes to existing buildings, buildings demolished for development, and general streetscape photographs of the Old and Historic District documenting its appearance from 1990 to 2004 (with one 1974 photograph). The photographs were taken by the Preservation Planner of the Department of Planning, Zoning & Development of the Town of Leesburg.
77 of the folders contain photographs, some with their negatives; two folders contain maps (the Old & Historic District 2004, and a map of Goshen just outside the town); one folder contains 25 sets of negatives that do not exactly match any other particular folders that are listed separately; one folder is miscellaneous material. There is also a set of plans for the John Janney House at 10 Cornwall St. N.E. in the Historic District.
The buildings photographed are generally identified by address and further information may be accessed in Leesburg Architectural Surveys (M 016) which are listed by address, as well as by the state's identifying number and by the county's tax map numbers.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Cox, Teckla, retired Loudoun County Planner, 2007.
Town of Leesburg, VA, Department of Planning, Zoning and Development, http://www.leesburgva.gov/services/planning/. (accessed 29 Aug 2007).
Town of Leesburg: Department of Planning, Zoning & Development: Visual Records of Historic Sites (RG 22), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Other Finding Aid
None
Related Material
Leesburg Architectural Surveys 1971-2001 (M 016), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Ceremonies, 1994-2000
  - Aerial Photographs with negatives 1996, 2001
  - Mighty Midget - documents re: town preservation, renovation & lease, n.d.
  - Mighty Midget, n.d.
  - Negatives
    1. 1997 Leesburg Corner site before development
    2. 1997 Cornwall St.; Market St.; Barn behind 107 S King St.
    3. Moving 6 & 8 Loudoun (Tolbert building) to 108 Church St. SE
    4. Tolbert building
    5. Survey photographs S King St., W Market St., Ayr St.
    6. Blossom & Bloom Y alley beside it
    7. S King St.; also houses added to Old & Historic District
  - Harper stone house - prior to move, moving process, post move
  - Harper stone house - prior to move, moving process, post move n.d.
  - W Market St. prior to addition to historic district, n.d.
  - S King St. prior to addition to historic district, n.d.
  - 223 Royal St. (demolished), n.d.
  - 234 Loudoun St (demolished), n.d.
  - 206 W Market St. (demolished), n.d.
  - 13, 15 E Royal (demolished) n.d.
  - 116 E Market (Glembot smokehouse) (demolished), n.d.
  - Sycolin Rd., burned house (demolished), n.d.
  - Ruins of Exeter main house prior to construction of WalMart, n.d.
  - Lombardy Farm (demolished), n.d.
- (Box 2)
  - Exeter overseers house (Walmart site - demolished), n.d.
  - 107 Royal St., n.d.
  - Whitmore/Littlejohn house (once part of Exeter), ruin & restoration, n.d.
  - 7 E. Market S, before renovation, n.d.
  - 6, 8 Loudoun St. SW (Tolbert building), moved to 108 Church St. SE, n.d.
  - Tavistock - outbuildings demolished; house now community center, n.d.
  - Kincaid Farm, n.d.
  - Outbuilding 109 S King St., n.d.
  - Houses demolished for court building, 2001
  - 241 W Market St., ca. 1995
  - Entrenchment and map, ca. 1995
  - Goshen map, ca. 1995
  - Mouth of Goose Creek (now River Creek development), ca. 1995
  - Shreve house (now Highpoint 1991), ca. 1995
  - Route 7 at Goose Creek, ca. 1995
  - Houses demolished for Leesburg Corner, ca. 1995
  - Laurel Brigade Inn, ca. 1995
  - Potter's Field, ca. 1995
  - Waverly, 1997
  - Stowers Farm, ca. 1995
  - Demolished house - E Market St., ca. 1995
  - S King St. - Safeway, ca. 1995
  - Bypass, ca. 1995
  - E Market St. near Best Western Hotel, ca. 1995
  - Linden Hill - outside town on Route 15 S, ca. 1995
  - Route 7 E outside town limits, ca. 1995
  - Unidentified, ca. 1995
  - Route 7 E - Cardinal Park, ca. 1995
  - Silver Mining Camp, ca. 1995
  - E Market St. - Douglass School (National Register), & vicinity, ca. 1995
  - E Market St. General views; includes aerials, ca. 1995
  - Route 7 E - Carodoc Hall, ca. 1995
  - Route 7 E - office development, ca. 1995
  - Map of Historic District - 2004, ca. 1995
  - Airport, ca. 1995
  - Looking north on Sycolin Rd., 1990s
  - Meeting with David Brown, late 1990s
  - Retail signs in Hilton Head & other cities, ca. 1995
  - Mount Zion Methodist Church - North St., ca. 1995
  - Market St., ca. 1995
- (Box 3)
  - King St., ca. 1995
  - Wirt Street, ca. 1995
  - Loudoun St., ca. 1995
  - Cornwall St., ca. 1995
  - Market Station - before construction, ca. 1995
  - Log cabin on Wirt St., ca. 1995
  - 6 & 8 Loudoun (Talbot building) before move to Church St., ca. 1995
  - North St. (Murders Bay), ca. 1995
  - Liberty St. (Baby St.), ca. 1995
  - Old Town Office - formerly auto dealership (Buick), ca. 1995
  - Thomas Balch Library renovation, ca. 1995
  - Consultants' photos of Leesburg corridor - Routes 7 & 15, ca. 1995
  - Courthouse lawn dig, ca. 2000
  - Belmont Forest, ca. 1995
  - Edwards Ferry Rd., ca. 1995
  - Barn demolished for Leesburg Commons, ca. 1995
  - 407 S King St. - demolished outbuilding, ca. 1995
  - Loudoun Museum tour & presentation ca. 1995
  - Historic District downtown, 1999
  - Leesburg Inn - demolished for County Building; now Clerk's Office, ca. 1995
  - Court buildings, 1974
  - Inside Leesburg, 1992
  - Doors & windows, ca. 1995
  - Sycolin Rd., ca. 1995
  - Construction County office building, 1990s
  - Edwards Ferry Rd., ca. 1995
  - Cornwall and Church St. - demolition of house
  - 24 W Market St. fire
  - Miscellaneous, ca. 1995
  - Negatives, 1990-2001
    1. Greenway
    2. Route 7 - 1990
    3. 7 E Market St: Raymond Group House; Farm on Route 7/15 bypass
    4. Stone Harper House; S King St; Church St.; House on Sycolin Rd.
    5. Aerial photos spring 1997; River Creek; Potomac Station; Goshen; Leesburg Corner
    6. Historic District 1995; Goshen at River Creek; Potomac Station
    7. Loudoun St. Victorian; 9 Church St.; porches & doorways
    8. Route 7 E (town & county)
    9. Unidentified
    10. 107 Royal St. SW; 303 & 305 S King St. 1998
    11. Various Old & Historic District
    12. Peoples Bank (Lightfoot Restaurant) & Courthouse lawn dig
    13. W Market St; Old & Historic District
    14. Dodona Manor 1991
    15. Doors & windows; 2 W Market St. 1993
    16. Courthouse Library exhibit March/April 1998
    17. E Market St. 1999 Old & Historic District
    18. Construction of Harper Stone House April 1996; 241 E Market St
    19. Flags
    20. Downtown Leesburg commercial
    21. Black school house on Union St.; William Johnson house; 50 Edwards Ferry Rd; Chevy Chase Ct.; N King St.
    22. Historic District 1999
    23. 307, 407 S King St
    24. S King St. & Edwards Ferry Rd. - 2000-2001 grant projects
    25. Historic sites in Joint Land Management Area or Urban Growth Area - September 2001
  - Negatives
    1. Greenway Farm
    2. Demolished building, Royal St., King St., Market St.
    3. Route 15 N
    4. Edwards Ferry Road 3rd Expansion 1990
    5. Stone House Rt. 15 Bypass
    6. Harper Stone House
    7. H-2 Projects
    8. Glembot Smokehouse W Market Street 1991
    9. Rt. 7 demolished barn
    10. Stone house Rt. 7, interior 19 King St., outbuilding Liberty St.
    11. Rt. 7 E
    12. S King St. 1993
    13. 19 E Market St., 222 W Market, Courthouse Excavation, stone house
    14. Log house, Loudoun St
    15. E Market St. 1990
    16. Ida Lee
    17. Architectural Features
    18. Plaza St. dedication 1997
    19. Friends of Thomas Balch Library news conference
    20. Catoctin State park opening 1998
    21. Christmas downtown 1999
    22. Arbor Day tree planning 1999
    23. Loudoun Museum Civil War sign installation
  - Negatives - old and historic district
  - Slides - manager's cottage Exeter
  - CD - grant photos Civil War building survey
  - CD - Laurel Brigade 2004 renovation
  - CD - unidentified
- (Rolled Storage)
  - Plans -- John Janney House, 10 Cornwall St. NE n.d.